<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Uno]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Uno</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 15:52:01 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 15:52:01 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[Introduction]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>What is more fearsome than the monsters of our own making?<br>
Version: 0.9.2<br><br>The Menagerie Esoterica is a no-prep, narrative-focused tabletop roleplaying game where you and some friends use a deck of tarot cards to craft a monster then play the fools unfortunate enough to face it. It is meant to be played without a GM and without any prep, with the world, the details, and—most importantly—the monster being conjured from whole cloth over the course of the session.<br><br>
<br>a Rider-Waite-Smith style tarot deck
<br>a stack of blank index cards
<br>pens, markers, crayons, or anything else with which to draw but not erase
<br>a handful of tokens such as coins, beads, or paperclips
<br>1–4 players
<br>90–120 minutes
<br><br>Instead of dice, Menagerie Esoterica uses a Rider-Waite-Smith style tarot deck for randomization. We are only concerned with the cards as literal playing cards, not necessarily their style or symbolism (though by all means use them if you wish!). If you have a different type of tarot deck, or if you're unsure of what type of deck you have in the first place, so long as there are 78 cards categorized into four suits and 22 major arcana, and so long as the drawings have a clear up and down, then that deck can be used with this system. A virtual deck can also be used if it allows for randomly drawing cards in reverse.<br>If you're only familiar with 52 card playing card decks, there is some extra terminology that we use in Menagerie Esoterica:<br>
<br>The Minor Arcana are the 56 cards ranked and organized into 4 suits (Wands, Cups, Swords, Pentacles), similar to a 52 card deck
<br>The Major Arcana are the 22 additional cards marked by roman numerals, ie II The High Priestess and XIII Death.
<br>Cards are illustrated with an orientation that can be viewed right-side up or upside down. If the card is drawn right-side up (from the perspective of the person who drew), it is Upright; if the card is drawn upside down, it is Reversed.
<br><br>At any point when you draw a card and have to refer to a table, ie when creating the situation or monster, you may ignore the table and instead use the illustration and related symbolism for your drawn card as inspiration to answer a prompt.<br><br>Menagerie Esoterica can be played in a single session with no prior preparation. It is divided into two phases:<br>
<br>In the Creation phase, players draw tarot cards to create Truths about the setting and the monster, as well as defining the characters that find themselves in this danger. There is no Game Master to create the world and the encounter; instead we use tarot cards to look up entries in various tables, and then let the players' imaginations paint in the connective, finer details.
<br>In the Engagement phase, players take turns performing Gambits, each describing how their character acts in the face of the monster while using Truths to justify the scene, then resolving the action by drawing tarot cards. In addition to deciding success and failure, the tarot cards will pose Queries, asking how the situation progresses or becomes more complicated, thus giving space for players to fill in details and nuance to make their monster truly unique and terrifying. Narrative progression is then recorded symbolically onto the Truth cards.
<br><br>At the core of Menagerie Esoterica are Truths. Truths initially get recorded on index cards as a name and icon and serve as springboards and pillars to create more ideas. Over the course of play, players will draw more icons on them as the situation evolves, essentially creating their own unique esoterica.<br>When creating a Truth card, take a blank index card and orient it vertically. Summarize the Truth to a 1-3 word name and write this at the bottom of the card. Take no more than one (1) minute to sketch an icon in the center of the card representing the Truth, leaving plenty of room for more icons to be added. Finally, start a tally with one (1) tick at the top of the card.<br>Example
<img alt="truth_card.svg" src="menagerie-esoterica/monstrum-assets/truth_card.svg">
<br><br>Typically, shuffling a deck seven (7) times will fully randomize the card order. However, we need to make sure cards can be drawn in a random orientation as well. When cutting the deck to shuffle, turn one half 180°, but otherwise proceed with your shuffling as normal to create a single draw pile.<br>After drawing cards (and unless otherwise stated), place them in a discard pile face up next to the draw pile. Whenever the discard pile is clearly taller than the draw pile, shuffle the two back together to form a new draw pile.<br><br>Some mechanics ask that players order their cards, ie when determining turn order. To put it simply, we only look at the number on the card regardless of suit. For unnumbered cards, we have Ace as equivalent to 1, Page as 11, Knight as 12, Queen as 13, and King as 14. Draw again to resolve ties.<br><br><br>Before all else, the world must be made. <br>To set the themes for the session, the players must first answer one question: are you the hunters or the hunted? Is this a monster hunt with a party of competent hunters going into the wilderness to claim their trophy? Is this a horror, where characters are not expected to live past the first act, let alone until the end?<br>If there is no strong consensus either way, draw one (1) card. If it is Reversed, the party is the hunted. If it is Upright, the party is the hunter.<br>Now we must get the general setting. Draw cards until one (1) Minor Arcana is found. Use the rank and orientation of the card with the table below to get a descriptor for the location.<br><br>Next, have each player draw and reveal one (1) card at a time until a Major Arcana is found. Use the table below to determine the setting's physical location.<br><br>Record the descriptor and location on the bottom of a blank index card. In the center of the card, draw a quick icon representing the locale. Don't spend more than a minute drawing this as we will be adding more icons and symbology over the course of the game. This card becomes the session's first Truth.<br>Discard all drawn tarot cards.<br><br>Truths paint the setting with specific, evocative details such as the literal physical objects in a scene, peculiarities of the monster's behavior, and even background lore and history. Each Truth is recorded on its own index card, and most importantly, they are mutable. Over the course of the Engagement, Truths will evolve and morph as players answer Queries, bringing in new elements that can help or complicate the situation as it unfolds.<br><br>Have each player draw as many cards as specified above and go around in order from highest to lowest. Each player says 1–2 sentences as a Truth about the world. Players may use the drawn card's rank with the table below as inspiration for the nature of their Truth, or they may come up with their own. Other players may collaborate and give input. <br>Finally, give the Truth a name. Record this name at the bottom of a blank index card, and spend no more than one (1) minute drawing an icon at the center of the card to represent it. <br>Once all players have finished creating their Truth(s), place all Truth cards in the center of the play area and discard all drawn tarot cards.<br><br><br>Finally, determine why you are here. Each player draws one (1) card. Go around from highest to lowest, suggesting in one sentence why the group is here. Discuss for a maximum of five minutes, picking and choosing from all suggestions. The goal for this final step is to make sure the players are all in the same headspace before moving on to character creation.<br>Example
Some reasons why the party may be here:

<br>we all just woke up here
<br>we're a group of teens and a dog and our van broke down
<br>we're a squad of commandos sent to investigate

<br><br>Example
BECKANY: First question: are we the hunters or the hunted?<br>
HAWTHORNE: I'm feeling the hunted.<br>
MILDRED: Agreed.<br>
BECAKNY: Thirded! Now we each draw cards until we find a Minor Arcana. I pull... 5 of Swords.<br>
MILDRED: That corresponds with Bloody.<br>
BECKANY: Ok, now let's go around until we find a Major Arcana to see what this Bloody place is. I got the 10 of Wands. Nope.<br>
HAWTHORNE: 8 of Pentacles.<br>
MILDRED: Knight of Wands.<br>
BECKANY: Aha! III The Empress. This puts us in the Bloody Circus.<br>
HAWTHORNE: Cheery.<br>
BECKANY: Well, let's spruce it up a bit. Time to add in some Truths. Everyone draw a card and we'll go from highest to lowest.<br>
MILDRED: I drew the Page of Pentacles so I go first by telling a "Truth about the history and tradition." Let's say the Bloody Circus was a gladiator arena that disappeared long ago, but suddenly appeared now.<br>
HAWTHORNE: Oh, gladiators are fun. I drew IV The Emperor so I can go next. "A Truth about something commonly found." Let's keep going with the gladiator theme. Swords and spears litter the area, seemingly covered in fresh blood.<br>
BECKANY: I feel like we're not sprucing up the place very well. I drew the 3 of Pentacles, which asks for a "Truth about stone and rock". What if the rocks are very polite but only if you speak to them softly?<br>
HAWTHORNE: Honestly, I love that. The rocks have seen so much.<br>
MILDRED: They know what happens to those who are rude.<br>
BECKANY: Yeah! Alright, each of us draws one more time so we can suggest why we are here. I got XIV Temperance so I go first. What if we're here purely on accident. We were just minding our business and the Bloody Circus appeared around us.<br>
HAWTHORNE: I got X Wheel of Fortune so I'm next. Maybe we're here because of a mad wizard who just summoned random people for an anime tournament arc.<br>
MILDRED: 3 of Wands. Strength. Effort. Commerce. I think we were here with purpose to watch the gladiator fights. However, a monster escaped.<br>
BECKANY: Right! Let's unify all those. I kinda like the idea that we were here on purpose, but maybe not as spectators?<br>
HAWTHORNE: You mean like we came to fight? But aren't we supposed to be the hunted?<br>
BECKANY: Maybe we drew the short straw or something.<br>
MILDRED: The mad wizard's champion already defeated and devoured all the strongest warriors. We're all that's left to stop the mad wizard from world domination.<br>
BECKANY: Hell yeah.
<br><br>Once we know the situation, we can create our characters. Like Truths, a character sheet will just be recorded on an index card. Have each player draw one (1) card and go from highest to lowest, telling one another your character's name and Specialty.<br>Every individual is as baseline competent as the agreed upon themes, but they have come together as a party because each brings a Specialty that the others aren't quite as good at. Specialties are meant to be broad, and like Truths, will get riffed off of and further refined over the course of the Engagement. For example, inventories are not precisely tracked and instead players may freely conjure items from their packs and pockets if it makes sense within the context of their Specialty.<br>Example
Specialties might be along the lines of:

<br>Marksmanship
<br>Driving
<br>Animal Handling
<br>Structural Engineering
<br>Parkour
<br>Big and strong
<br>Fireball

<br>Record the name of your character on a blank index card, draw an icon in the center of the card representing their Specialty, and start a tally with one (1) tick at the top of the card. Character cards are Truths, and each card can be placed in front of their respective player.<br>With the stage dressed and the actors present, we now drop them in media res with the monster's first sighting.<br><br><br>The earth rumbles in heart-shaking bass under an echoing snarl that grows from the darkness. What brings the beast here? What is its Drive? The monster is in conflict with the players for a reason, and understanding this reason may help resolve the situation.<br>Draw one (1) card and place it horizontally in the center of the play area. Use the below table to determine the monster’s Drive according to the drawn card’s suit.<br><img alt="drive.svg" src="menagerie-esoterica/monstrum-assets/drive.svg"><br><br>Recall why you are here. Have each player draw one (1) card and go from highest to lowest with each player speculating about the Nature of the Beast, and why this has brought the monster into conflict with the party. All of these are true. None of these are True. Discard the drawn tarot cards.<br><br>The monster emerges, its silhouette now coming into terrifying focus. Have each player draw and reveal one (1) card at a time until a Major Arcana is found. Discard any Minor Arcana. The Major Arcana defines the monster's Body Plan, ie its general shape and silhouette. Place the Major Arcana vertically over the Drive card, making a cross and forming the monster's Core.<br><img alt="core.svg" src="menagerie-esoterica/monstrum-assets/core.svg"><br><br>As the party first lays eyes on the monster's main bulk, recall the setting. Is this the monster's natural habitat? Or does it stand in stark contrast, an unnatural abomination in a place that it should not be?<br>Give the monster a name and write it at the bottom of a blank index card, then draw an icon representing the monster's Core at the center of the card. Start a tally at the top of the card with one (1) tick to finish creating a new Truth.<br><br>An awesome shadow renders further into grotesque detail. With the monster's drive and body defined, we must now give it Aspects. <br><br>Have each player, one at a time, draw and reveal cards until they draw one (1) Minor Arcana. Discard any Major Arcana drawn. Use the table below to determine the Aspect. Give one or two sentences describing how the monster is draped in this power or how the environment warps under its might. All players are invited to collaborate once the first player has had their initial say. Use the table above to determine how many Aspects to draw.<br>Many Aspects may at first seem to contradict each other, but every player is invited to make sense of any disparities together, ideally rendering a monster that is both unique and personal to the session and game lore. However, the creation of a monster is at the end of the day fiction first—if an aspect doesn't fit, feels redundant, or even if you've just seen it too recently, simply discard it and draw another card.<br>Once satisfied, create a new Truth card by writing the name of the Aspect at the bottom of a blank index card and drawing an icon that represents it in the center. Start a tally with one (1) tick at the top of the card.<br><br><br>Some monsters have an affinity to a particular element which can flavor its Aspects. The specific element can be left up to the players, using what makes sense for the Situation and its Truths, or they can draw one (1) card and use the table below for inspiration. Discard the card afterward.<br>Similarly, the effects of poison can be left up to players as they role play, or the table below can be consulted.<br><br>Reposition Truth cards around the monster's Core, shuffle all discarded cards back into the draw pile, then begin the Engagement.<br><br>Example
Having finished creating the situation and characters for The Ethereal Catacombs, Ndlovu, Clef, Vikram, and Lei move on to create the monster
NDLOVU: Okay, drawing for the Drive I've got... the 9 of Pentacles. Pentacles means Treasure. The reason why we're here was because we were laying my grandmother's ashes to rest. Everyone draw a card and we'll go highest to lowest to suggest the Nature of the Beast.<br>
CLEF: I got the Page of Cups which is highest so let's go with the the obvious one to get it out of the way: the urn we're holding is made of gold and studded with jewels.<br>
LEI: I have 8 of Pentacles. What if one of us pocketed something from another shrine and this is the catacomb guardian?<br>
VIKRAM: I'll go next with the VI The Lovers... let's say the treasure the monster seeks is the ash itself? Or the soul?<br>
NDLOVU: All these are great. So as the last idea, maybe the monster likes to collect fresh heads.<br>
CLEF: Me next, for the Body Plan I draw... King of Swords. Dang, that's a Minor Arcana. Guess I pass.<br>
VIKRAM: No worries. I got II The High Priestess. Arborescent? Not really sure what to make of that aside from what it just says—a tree. Not much of those underground.<br>
CLEF: What if we just think about the trunk? I'm imagining like a pillar. Something tall and vertical. Like it could have been mistaken for a supporting structure here.<br>
LEI: Yeah! Maybe it really is just like a literal pillar of gold or something like that?<br>
NDLOVU: Oooh, and it's carved with hundreds of faces!<br>
VIKRAM: You're really going all in on the collecting heads thing.<br>
NDLOVU: I just think they're neat.<br>
LEI: Same. Now what's this guy's name?<br>
NDLOVU: Pillar of Gold is right there.<br>
VIKRAM: How about the Facets of Avarice?<br>
CLEF: That rocks. Writing that down on a new index card, and I'm gonna draw a pillar with some smiley faces on it.<br>
LEI: Nice. Let's go onto Aspects. One each, right?<br>
CLEF: Yeah.<br>
LEI: Hmm. I drew 0 The Fool. That's not a Minor Arcana so it's not in the table.<br>
CLEF: Go ahead and keep drawing.<br>
LEI: Alright. Now I got 6 of Swords in reverse. That's Spines. What if each carved face has sharpened spikes where their eyes should be?<br>
NDLOVU: Terrible. I love it.<br>
LEI: I'll name this new Truth card Pierced Visage and draw a face with spikes coming out of it.<br>
NDLOVU: Okay me next. Knight of Swords in reverse which is Strong Bite. Oh man I hate to do this but the faces must be animated with working jaws. Probably screaming, too.<br>
LEI: Definitely a lot of wailing and gnashing of teeth.<br>
NDLOVU: Let's just call this Truth Grimace. Here's some teeth.<br>
CLEF: Cool. So next I've got the 5 of Wands also in reverse. Did we shuffle this right? Why are all these cards upside down?<br>
VIKRAM: That's just how coin flips work, dude.<br>
CLEF: Whatever. That Aspect is Poison Coat. I think that's pretty obvious.<br>
NDLOVU: Describe what we see.<br>
CLEF: Hmm... we see the glint of gold—shining and and resplendent even in the flickering ghostlight of the catacombs—but as the monster comes closer and our eyes adjust we see an irridescent sheen of oil slicked over gold. The stale underground air shifts with the behemoths movement, and a scent touches our nostrils with an acrid singe.<br>
NDLOVU: Hell yeah. What's the new Truth called?<br>
CLEF: Tarnished Gold.<br>
VIKRAM: Last but not least, me! 7 of Wands, upright. Told you that's how coin flips work. Looks like the monster has a Big Sword.<br>
LEI: Oh god.<br>
VIKRAM: I'm going to riff off the Spines and Strong Bite. Ok so once the monster is within "big sword range"—we all know what that is—<br>
LEI: For sure.<br>
NDLOVU: Definitely.<br>
VIKRAM: —we see one of the faces extrude out from the pillar. It bends around and chomps down on one of the biggest spines nearby and pulls sharply, the gold moving at first like a whip then quickly forming into a gigantic khopesh. I'll name the new Truth Hunger for Conquest.<br>
LEI: Alright! Let's do this.
<br>TODO diagram this monster's Truth as an example<br><br><br><img alt="play area.svg" src="menagerie-esoterica/monstrum-assets/play-area.svg"><br>
The Engagement begins with players setting a Goal and drawing one (1) card face down to represent Fate and to hold their progress tokens. <br>Once the Goal is set, play is organized into rounds, called Antes. At the start of each Ante, a Query is posed, introducing context and complications into the Engagement. Players then take turns each performing one (1) Gambit, where they describe what their character does in the face of the monster, and how they take advantage of Truths to further progress to the Goal.<br>A Gambit's outcome is determined by drawing tarot cards. Positive outcomes further progress to the Goal, while negative outcomes introduce complications. Regardless of outcome, a Query is posed, and the answer is recorded as a new icon on a Truth card, modifying its meaning.<br><br>Start the Engagement by deciding on a Goal. We know how the party got here, but with a monster suddenly threatening them, we need to know what the party intends to do now.<br>Example
 Examples of Goals might be:

<br>The party is here to hunt the monster and put an end to its reign of terror, and so hunt it they shall.
<br>Scientists want to study the monster and create a theme park so the party is here to capture it live.
<br>A loved one was transformed into the monster, so the party wants to mollify and turn it.
<br>The monster has killed everyone else, and the party only wants to survive long enough to take the last escape pod.
<br>The monster guards an invaluable treasure. All the party has to do is take it and make sure the monster does not follow.
<br>A villain is making his escape and summons a monster to buy time. The party must contend with the threat while capturing their target.

<br>The Goal may not necessarily be about killing the monster, and so we do not define the Engagement in terms of hit points; instead we define the Engagement in terms of progress and Fate. Draw one (1) card but keep it face down. Place it to the right of the monster's core. This is the Fate deck. As the party makes progress on their goal, more face-down cards will be added to this pile, only to be revealed when the party decides to Take Decisive Action.<br>Players may change the Goal at any time, so long as everyone is in agreement—after all, the difference between flight and fight rides a fine knife's edge.<br><br>Each round begins with a Query, which poses a question that changes the current situation and must be solved or worked around by the party. At the start of the round when a new Query must be posed, draw one (1) card. This is the Query card. Use it in conjunction with the Ante to determine the Query. All Engagements start at Ante 1.<br><br>Ask the Query out loud so that it can be discussed as a group, rephrasing and injecting context to make it relevant to the session. Describe how the answer to the Query changes the Situation, calling out any new dangers and complications. Record the answer to the Query by drawing a new icon or symbol on at least two (2) relevant Truth cards.<br>Finally, place the Query card to the left of the monster's Core. Place four (4) tokens on it. These are Progress Tokens, representing the remaining time in the round. As players play successful Gambits, they will take tokens from this pile and place them atop the Fate deck.<br><br>The Ante represents the rising stakes as the players get closer to their Goal but draw the increasing attention and ire of the monster. The Ante starts at 1 at the beginning of the Engagement, and will increase over the course of the game to a maximum of four (4). The Ante is tracked by the number of cards in the Fate deck.<br>When all four (4) tokens have been taken from the Query card, the current round ends and the Ante is increased. Remove the tokens from the Fate deck and draw one (1) tarot card. Keeping it face-down, place it atop the Fate deck.<br>The Ante is tracked by the number of cards in the Fate deck. At the beginning of the Engagement, one (1) face-down tarot card is already in place after deciding on the Goal. At the beginning of each subsequent Ante, draw one (1) tarot card and place it atop the Fate deck, keeping it face-down, thus increasing the Ante by one (1) level. <br>Draw and reveal one (1) more tarot card and place it to the left of the monster's Core. This is the new Query card for the round. Answer it as a group, then place four (4) progress tokens on it. Proceed with each player taking turns until the round ends, and repeat.<br>At the end of Ante 4 (ie when there are four (4) cards in the Fate deck and no progress tokens remaining on the Query card), the party must Take Decisive Action.<br><br>Players take turns performing Gambits to make progress on the party's Goal in the face of the monster. Turn order is not set; the only rule is that a player may not perform two Gambits in a row (unless playing solo). This is intentionally left loose as action should first follow the fiction and flow between each player as it makes sense; however, we want to ensure space for everyone to take center stage and shine.<br>The player turn can be broken into three steps:<br>
<br>Perform a Gambit. The player describes the action their character does, referencing one or more Truths to explain why their action may be effective.
<br>Read the Outcome. The player draws 3 tarot cards, with the orientation of drawn cards determining success or failure.
<br>Illustrate Icons. The player answers Queries posed by the drawn cards by drawing new icons on relevant Truth cards.
<br><br>Gambits are the risky, audacious action(s) that a character does in the face of the monster, the outcomes of which are resolved by drawing tarot cards. However, the monster is a force of nature and without a deliberate approach, no progress will be made; therefore, a Gambit is composed not only of the action, but must also be accompanied by one or more Truths.<br>Actions taken when not under threat of the monster such as walking, talking, and observing are considered free in that we don't need to draw to resolve them. The player characters are at a baseline of competence; if the monster can't directly or indirectly thwart the player's action then there is no reason for them to fail.<br>To perform a Gambit, the player gathers at least one (1) and at most (4) Truth cards. The player then describes how their character acts, using the gathered Truths as touch points to explain why their character is able to perform the action and why they think it should be effective. Players are invited to conjure new details, lore, backstory, etc. so long as they make sense within the gathered Truths' context and so long as previously established details are not contradicted.<br>Example
Examples of Gambits might include:

<br>Leonid tries to hide from the monster. He gathers the Mind Sense Truth, saying he's hiding by imagining himself far away by the ocean. He also gathers the Ancient High School Truth, saying that he's actually hiding in the bathroom and flushing a toilet to help him visualize waves.
<br>Kim shoots an arrow at the monster's eyes. She gathers the Arcane Glyphs Truth, saying the monster's eyes glow with sigils and must be the source of its magic, as well as gathering her own character's Truth to reference her Specialty of Marksmanship. Rickolas offers his own Specialty of Big and Strong, saying that he is taunting the monster so that its wide-eyed gaze focuses on him.
<br>Pilbin tries to evade the monster and capture its true master by running along the rooftops. They gather the Tentacles Truth, their own Specialty of Parkour, and the Opaque Fog Truth, saying that the monster's slimy limbs will desiccate if they rise out of the mists.
<br>Veronicole closes her eyes and bows. She gathers the Invisibility Truth and the Respected Old Ways Truth, saying that the old folk tales emphasize respect and mention invisible creatures simply wanting to hide, and that by closing her eyes of her own volition, she shows respect for the monster's desire to be unseen.

<br><br>For every Truth gathered, draw and reveal one (1) tarot card. Choose the best outcome.<br><br><br>If at least one (1) Major Arcana is drawn upright, then the Gambit was fully successful. Envision the triumph and how your intuition about the gathered Truths led to your success. On at least one (1) of the gathered Truth cards, illustrate a new icon that represents any new lore, details, or outcomes from the played Gambit as it relates to said Truth.<br>Move two (2) progress tokens from the Query to Fate. <br><br>If at least one (1) Minor Arcana was drawn upright but there were no upright Major Arcana, then the Gambit was still successful but there is a toll to be paid. Envision the success and the fleeting feeling of victory before the complications reared their head. Use the suit of the drawn Minor Arcana to determine the nature of the complications.<br><br>On at most one (1) relevant Truth, illustrate a new icon that represents any new lore or details from the Gambit's success. On at least one (1) Truth (it can be the same), illustrate a new icon that represents the complications and harm that arose.<br>Move one (1) progress token from the Query to Fate.<br><br>If no cards were drawn upright, then the Gambit was a disaster. Whether by poor assumptions, bad footing, or simple bad luck, the situation worsens. Envision the catastrophe, using the suit of any drawn card to determine its nature. <br><br>On at least two (2) relevant Truths, illustrate a new icon representing the disaster.<br><br>As Gambits are played and the Ante increases, players will be asked to illustrate new icons on Truth cards. Spend no more than 30 seconds drawing an icon. While the envisioned successes and failures  can be filled with detail, the icons themselves should remain basic and up to interpretation. <br>Icons are representations, not reminders. After all, a disadvantage one moment can become advantageous the next; or vice versa.<br>When modifying a Truth with an icon, you may draw over and around existing icons; however, you may not erase them. After adding a new icon to a Truth, add one (1) tick to the tally at the top of the card.<br><br>At any point during the Engagement, or at the end of Ante 4, the party may Take Decisive Action and collectively describe how they bring the encounter to a close. Reveal all cards in the Fate deck, choose the best outcome below based on the cards' arcana and orientation, and answer the final Query as a group.<br><br>Regardless of the draw, the Engagement comes to a close, with the monster successfully slain, slaked, captured, or fled. Now you may Rest.<br>TODO example final Ante]]></description><link>menagerie-esoterica/menagerie-esoterica.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Menagerie Esoterica/Menagerie Esoterica.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 20:17:19 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="menagerie-esoterica/monstrum-assets/truth_card.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="menagerie-esoterica/monstrum-assets/truth_card.svg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>